<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fauourite: or, A plaine demonstration from Holy Scripture of Gods especiall loue to the righteous, in a sermon preached at S. Andrewes in Norwich, the 18. of Nouemb. 1611. since enlarged and newly published for the comfort of Gods people. By Timo: Plummer preacher of Gods word</title>
            <author>Plummer, Timothy.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09780</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20050</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105176</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840906</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840906</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5450</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09780)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5450)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 932:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fauourite: or, A plaine demonstration from Holy Scripture of Gods especiall loue to the righteous, in a sermon preached at S. Andrewes in Norwich, the 18. of Nouemb. 1611. since enlarged and newly published for the comfort of Gods people. By Timo: Plummer preacher of Gods word</title>
                  <author>Plummer, Timothy.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 45, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Man, dwelling in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the Swanne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On D7v, final leaf: I.S. to the reader (in verse).</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5450:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5450:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FAVOVRITE: <hi>OR,</hi> A plaine Demonſtration from Holy Scripture of Gods eſpeciall loue to the righteous, in a Sermon preached at S.
<hi>Andrewes</hi> in <hi>Norwich,</hi> the 18. of <hi>Nouemb.</hi> 1625. ſince enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and newly publiſhed for the Comfort of Gods people.</p>
            <p>By TIMO: PLVMMER Preacher of Gods Word.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 1. verſ. 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Lord knoweth the way of the righteous, but the way of the wicked ſhall periſh.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prou. 11. verſ. 28.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He that truſteth in his riches ſhall fall, but the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſhall flouriſh as a Branch.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Samuel Man,</hi> dwelling in
<hi>Paules</hi> Church-yard at the ſigne of the Swanne. 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5450:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5450:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL MASTER GEORGE BIRCHE, now
<hi>Maior</hi> of the Citie of <hi>Norwich,</hi> to the Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sheriffes and Aldermen his Brethren, to the Commons and to all the Citizens in the ſame Cittie; <hi>Timothie Plummer</hi> wiſheth all happineſſe here, and hereafter the Crowne of Righteouſneſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT Worſhipfull and Right Chriſtian Friends, as I am wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to acknowledge Gods gracious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, and therein the manifold fauours receiued of and
<pb facs="tcp:5450:3"/>in the Citie of Norwich, for the ſpace of no leſſe then 14. yeeres, both from priuate perſons Chriſtianly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in the time I was a poore Grammer-ſcholler, and from publike Magiſtrates, godly and religious, who haue ſhewed me more then ordinarie fauour, partly in freely allowing me a yeerely penſion during the time I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued and proceeded in Cambridge, and partly in beſtowing vpon me, that painefull place which now by Gods bleſſing I doe enioy; I ſay, as I am willing to acknowledge theſe benefits with a thankfull minde, ſo I am as forward to expreſſe true and reall thankfulneſſe to euery one of you. I know very well that you will thinke your loue and coſt well beſtowed, if you may but ſee my profiting anſwer your expectation. And thus much I vnderſtand to my greater encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that my poore endeauours al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſhewed haue been of you, moſt
<pb facs="tcp:5450:3"/>louingly accepted; which I wiſh may be a teſtimonie vnto you, that I haue endeauoured (in ſome meaſure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire) to be faithfull in a little: And of all my meditations I know none haue had better acceptation, then this which I name the Fauourite; which kinde acceptance I may truly ſay, was the cauſe of publiſhing this little Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> But I ought not to be ignorant that this worke now muſt paſſe through the hands and cenſures of many ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, who peraduenture will not ſo kindly accept, nor ſo fauourably beare with the ſlips they meete with as you haue done.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I hope all Readers that are well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded, will eaſily bee entreated to take in good part my willing endeauor in this neceſſary Argument,<note place="margin">In magnis volitiſſe ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t eſt.</note> and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe in the whole diſcourſe they ſhall not be able to finde any one line which may <hi>make the heart of the
<pb facs="tcp:5450:4"/>righteous ſad whom God hath not made ſad;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 13.22.</note> 
               <hi>or ſtrengthen the hands of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, that he ſhould not returne from his wicked way:</hi> And now, all that I will ſay to you, to whom I owe ſo much, is this, If there bee any thing in this ſhort Sermon, (which God hath brought to my hand by his gratious Spirit) whereby any of you may bee furthered in the way of righteouſnes, I humbly praiſe Almightie God, and ſend it vnto you all as the firſt fruits in this kinde; the beſt New-yeeres gift that I haue, being the fitteſt token and teſtimonie of my vnfeined thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Further commending to your Chriſtian conſideration a place of Scripture, viz. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 33.12. &amp;c. vnto the 20. verſe, And adding this petition to the Father of lights from whome commeth euery good and perfect gift,<note place="margin">Iam.
1.17.</note> that he would be pleaſed to make you and me abound more and more in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery good word and worke,<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.17.</note> cauſing
<pb facs="tcp:5450:4"/>our pathes as the ſhining light to ſhine more and more vnto the perfect day,<note place="margin">Prou. 4.18.</note> I reſt and remaine. <hi>London</hi> this firſt of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> 1621.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in all offices of Chriſtianitie to bee commanded:</hi> Timo: Plummer.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:5450:5"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader, T. P. wiſheth all furtherance in the way of righteouſneſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, we finde in Hiſtory both Sacred and prophane, and eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerue in the practiſe of all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that Kings and Princes haue alwaies had ſome or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be their ſpeciall Fauourites, that is to ſay,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Such as they haue priuiledged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue others to bee moſt neere in atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance about their Royall perſons.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Such as they haue graced and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified
<pb facs="tcp:5450:5"/>with excellent names, ſtiles and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of honour.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Such as they acquaint with the greateſt and weightieſt ſecrets of State, admitting them to bee of their Priuie Councell.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> Such as they readily heare and grant petitioning and ſoliciting for themſelues and others.</p>
            <p>And nothing is more obutious in holy writ, then that God the King of Kings doth make the righteous man his onely Fauourite; The Lord ſets apart him that is godly for himſelfe.<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.3.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> He makes him attend vpon him in his ſpeciall preſence, in his Houſe, in his Courts, in the best place he hath: <hi>A day in thy Courts is better then a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal.
84.10.</note> I had rather be a doore-keeper in the houſe of my God then to dwell in the tents of wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> He giues him glorious names and titles, eſpecially, calling him The Sonne of God: <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith S. Iohn,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>what manner of loue the Father hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed
<pb facs="tcp:5450:6"/>vpon vs, that we ſhould be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ſonnes of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> He reucales to him his ſecrets, <hi>The ſecret of the Lord is with the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 3.32. Pſal. 25.14 Matth. 13.11.</note> 
               <hi>To you it is giuen to know the miſteries of the Kingdome of heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> Hee willingly heares his requeſts, put vp in the behalfe of himſelfe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>The feruent prayer of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous auayleth much.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 5.16. 1. Pet. 3.12. Ier. 14 11. Deut. 9.14.</note> It is ſtrange to obſerue how God ſeemeth to ſuffer vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence by their prayer: he is enforced to crie out, Pray not for this people, let me alone.</p>
            <p>And will you ſee all theſe particulars exemplified in one of Gods fauourites, namely, in faithfull and righteous <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> God takes him from Vr of the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does from Idolatrie and ſuperstition,<note place="margin">Gen. 11. &amp; 12. chap.</note> and entertaines him into his owne ſeruice; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenants to be his God, and commands him to walke before him and be vpright.<note place="margin">Gen.
17.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> His name is changed in token of further bleſſing, from <hi>Abram</hi> to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:5450:6"/>He muſt be a father of many nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the father of the faithfull,<note place="margin">Gen. 17.5. Rom. 4.13. Iam. 2.23.</note> the heire of the world, the friend of God, and what not?</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> God cannot finde in his heart to hide from
<hi>Abraham</hi> his ſecret purpoſe, ſhall I hide from <hi>Abraham</hi> the thing that I doe?<note place="margin">Gen. 18.19</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> He is allowed to be a Master of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts both for himſelfe and for others. As for <hi>Iſhmael</hi> I haue heard thee;<note place="margin">Gen 17.20</note> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I haue bleſſed him &amp; will make him fruitfull, &amp;c. Againe, God ſaith to <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech,</hi> Restore the man his wife,<note place="margin">Gen. 20.7</note> is a Prophet, and hee ſhall pray for thee and thou ſhalt liue: But marke how in one prayer he preuailed with God in the caſe of Sodome; obſerue, how ſoone hee brought God to an abatement;<note place="margin">Gen. 18.3</note> from fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to tenne: And I thinke if he had ſaid, If there ſhall bee found one righteous in the Cittie, God would haue ſpared it for ones ſake; This I am ſure of, that God neuer ceaſed granting till <hi>Abraham</hi> cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed praying. But to what end tendeth this
<pb facs="tcp:5450:7"/>diſcourſe? to comfort and encourage thee Oh Christian in theſe last and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillous times wherein wickedneſſe ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to get the vpper hand and true righteouſneſſe is outfaced.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.16 Mal. 3.15.</note> Wee may ſee
<hi>the place of iudgement, that wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is there; and the place of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, that iniquitie is there.</hi> What though Antichriſt for a time doe domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neere <hi>withall deceiueableneſſe of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe in them that periſh?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Theſſ. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>10.</note> what though the number of them be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed that
<hi>beleeue not the truth but haue pleaſure in vnrighteouſneſſe?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 12.</note> Bee not thou disheartened, let them feare the Spirit of Gods mouth and the brightnes of his comming;<note place="margin">Verſe 8.</note> but lift vp thy head; Be thou as bold as a Lyon,<note place="margin">Prou. 28.1</note> what though the wicked be rich and in amitie with the world?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.4.</note> thou art more rich; thou hast the better part, that ſhall neuer be taken from thee.<note place="margin">Prou. 8.13</note> 
               <hi>Durable riches and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,</hi> thou art most happy in Gods ſauour, if thou kneweſt thine owne hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe; and that thou mayeſt know
<pb facs="tcp:5450:7"/>it in ſome degree, I haue for thy ſake wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly publiſhed this little Treatiſe, It is my firſt borne, my might, and the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of my ſtrength; If thou reapest a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny profite by it, it is the thing which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, onely praiſe God in my behalfe, for enabling me to performe any ſeruice for the good of his Saints, and afford me thy prayers vnto the ſame God, that I may grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord Ieſus Christ.<note place="margin">2: Pet. 3.18</note>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy brother in the ſame Lord. <hi>T. P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:5450:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5450:8"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 37.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>A little that a righteous man hath, is better then the riches of many wicked.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eſides that maine and manifeſt diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence which God will make between the righteous and the wicked at the day of iudgement,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.18. Math. 13.43 Mat. 25.30.</note> when the righteous all ſhine foorth as the Sun, and the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be caſt into vtter darkeneſſe; Hee hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ade euen in this life a great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5450:9"/>them, not onely in reſpect of that inward portion of true ſanctifying grace, which the righteous partake inabundance, and the wicked not ſo much as taſt of, &amp; ſo differ as much as light and darkeneſſe; <hi>Ye were ſometimes darkeneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>but now are yee light in the Lord.</hi> But alſo in regard of their outward eſtate (which ſeemeth a Paradox) in temporals the righteous haue the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it, hee goeth away with the better ſhare; ſo ſaith this Text, <hi>A little that the righteous man hath is better then the riches of many wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Method which I vſe in the vnfol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of theſe words, is:
<list>
                  <item>1. I poynt out the righteous man.</item>
                  <item>2. I obſerue the little that he hath.</item>
                  <item>3. I ſhew how this little is better then the riches of many wicked.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, wee enquire for the Righteous man,<note place="margin">1. Part. Rom. 3.10. Eccl. 7.29 in Gen. 1.27</note> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> findeth it written, There is none righteous, no not one; <hi>Salomon</hi> hath onely found this, that God made man righteous, according to his owne image in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe. But as the Diuell ſtood not long in the truth, ſo man not long in that perfect eſtate, but by ſinne defaced Gods work of originall righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5450:9"/>both in himſelfe, and in his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity.<note place="margin">Gen. 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>Adam</hi> begat a ſonne in his owne likeneſſe, after his owne image, not in the image of God in which he was created, but in his owne image, that is, a ſinfull wretch like himſelfe. Hence <hi>Eliphaz</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Iob. 15.14. Eſay.
64.6.</note> what is man that he ſhould be cleane? and hee that is borne of a woman that hee ſhould bee righteous? And <hi>Eſay,</hi> we are all as an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane thing,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.19.</note> and al our righteouſneſſes are as filthy ragges; But the ſame Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith againe, <hi>As by one mans diſobedience many were made ſinners,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 53.11.</note> 
               <hi>ſo by the obedience of one</hi> (namely Chriſt) <hi>ſhall many be made righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous:</hi> according to that in the Prophet, by his knowledge ſhall my righteous ſeruant iuſtifie many.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.1. Ier. 23.5. &amp; 33.15. Mal. 4.2. Reu 12.1.</note> So then wee ſee that Gods children deriue all their righteouſnes from <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> the
<hi>Righteous;</hi> yea from that <hi>righteous Branch</hi> ſpring all their righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, they are couered about with the rayes and beames of
<hi>the Sunne of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi> The Church is cloathed with the Sunne.</p>
            <p>Now for the further clearing of this poynt, wee are ſayde to be righteous two wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By imputation of Chriſts righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5450:10"/>vnto vs, ſo Chriſt <hi>is made vnto vs</hi> (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other things) <hi>righteouſnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor.
1.30 2. Cor. 5.21. Rom. 10.4. Ier. 23.6. Iuſtitia E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelica. Phil. 3.9. Gen
15.6. Rom. 4.3, &amp;c.</note>and God hath made him to to be ſinne for vs, who knew no ſinne, that <hi>we might be made the righteouſnes of God in him.</hi> And in another place, <hi>Chriſt is the end of the law for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, to euery one that beleeueth,</hi> therefore we call him
<hi>the Lord our Righteouſneſſe,</hi> and this is called the righteouſneſſe of iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, or the righteouſneſſe of faith. An example of this wee may ſee in Abraham, <hi>He beleeued in the Lord, and he counted it to him for righteouſnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. By inchoation of inherent righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, wee being changed in our naturall qualities by the power of Chriſts Spirit, are led on to performe (in ſome meaſure) the righteouſnes of the morall Lawe, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the example of our Sauiour Chriſt;<note place="margin">1. Ioh.
3.7.</note> according to that pregnant place, <hi>He that doth righteouſnes, is righteous, euen as hee is righteous,</hi> and (this is called the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Sanctification, or the righteouſneſſe of the Lawe.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.4. Iuſtitia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galis. Pſal. 106.31</note> An example of this we hane in <hi>Phineas,</hi> who <hi>executed iudgement, and that was counted to him for righteouſnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:5450:10"/>
            <p>A Righteous man is ſuch an one as being found in ſinnefull
<hi>Adam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Righteous man. Epheſ.
2.3. Rom. 8.</note> a child of wrath, is through Gods e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall grace of election in Chriſt, called to be the Sonne of God, and heire of heauen, whoſe ſinne is freely pardoned, and perſon accepted in the actiue &amp; pasſiue righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Chriſt applyed by faith,<note place="margin">Mat.
3.17.</note> who being endued and renewed with the Spirit of Chriſt is ſo throughly altered and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in ſoule, body, and ſpirit,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.23.</note> that he is dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enabled to dye vnto ſinne, and to liue vnto righteouſnes, that is, willingly to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme ſome new and pleaſing obedience to Gods reuealed will, the onely rule of righteouſnes,<note place="margin">2. Cor 3.18. 1. Cor. 15.49.</note> and that from one degree vnto another, vntill at the laſt hee hath Gods image repayred and reſtored in as ample and better manner then euer it was at the firſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 17.15 Eph. 5.27.</note> to the prayſe and glory of Gods rich grace.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:5450:11"/>
            <p>VVHen on the contrary a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man is ſuch an one,<note place="margin">A deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a wicked man. Epheſ. 2.1. 1. Tim. 5 6. Eph.
4.18. 2. Tim. 2.26. Eph. 2.3. 1. Cor. 2.14. Phil. 2.13. Prou. 15.8. Eſa.
26.10.</note> as beeing the curſed off-ſpring of rebellious <hi>Adam,</hi> is by Gods eternall and iuſt appointment left in that damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble eſtate, who beeing dead in ſinnes and treſpaſſes, that is to ſay, hauing his minde darkened, his will captiuated, his affections diſordered, is not able to vnderſtand, will, or doe any thing pleaſing vnto God in the whole courſe of his life; yea notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all the meanes God vſeth, and fauour he ſheweth to reclayme him, there is none effectuall vnto him, he will not learne righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, but dayly walke in the willfull breach of Gods righteous Lawe, waxing worſe and worſe, and treaſuring vnto himſelfe wrath againſt the day of wrath,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.13 Rom. 2.5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and reuelation of the righteous iudgment of God.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:5450:11"/>
            <p>FIrſt if wee now make a ſuruay of the face of the world,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Vſe.</hi>
               </note> wee ſhall finde the wicked ſwarme and gather together in great multitudes, but for men qualified according to our deſcription of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man, the number will be very ſmall, ſo that we may haue iuſt cauſe to obſerue and bewaile the paucitie and fewneſſe of thoſe that are truly righteous: God in the old world found onely Noah <hi>that righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man, and a preacher of righteouſneſſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.5. Gen. 7.1.</note>
               <hi>Thee haue I found righteous before mee in this generation:</hi> In Sodom and Gomorrha there was not found ten righteons men, though they might haue ſaued the whole Cities from perdition,<note place="margin">Gen. 18.</note> Onely Lot <hi>is deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that righteous man that dwelt amongst them, who ſeeing and hearing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>vexed his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſoule from day to day, with their vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deedes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 1.8.</note> In Iobs time there was <hi>none like to him in the earth:</hi> Yea, it is the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all complaint of the Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,<note place="margin">Pſal. 12.1. Eſay 57.1. Mich. 7.2. Rom.
9.</note> that few are found walking in Gods righteous Law. And ſhall we that are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into the dregges of time, looke to ſinde a greater plentie, though wee ſearch the world with lights? But what ſhall we ſay or doe when wee finde ſuch ſcarcitie and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5450:12"/>want of righteouſneſſe on the earth? We muſt pray that <hi>righteouſnes may looke downe from heauen;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 85.11 Pſal. 4.1.</note> Let vs deſire the God of our righteouſneſſe to array the Church his Bride with fine linnen, cleane and white; the fine linnen is the righteouſneſſe of the Saints.<note place="margin">Reuel. 19.8</note> In particular, let vs put vp our ſuites in the behalfe of our Engliſh nation,<note place="margin">Prou. 14.34.</note> that righteouſneſſe may exalt it, and that ſinne may not be a reproach vnto it; In ſpeciall manner for the Kings moſt excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie,<note place="margin">Prou.
16.12. &amp; 25.5. Pſal. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1.</note> that his Royall throne may ſtill bee eſtabliſhed through righteouſneſſe. Giue thy iudgements oh Lord vnto the King, and thy righteouſneſſe vnto the Kings Sonne. Let vs not forget the Illuſtrious Prince and Princeſſe Palatine, with their hopefull iſſue, but pray, that God would bleſſe him in all his iuſt deſignes, that his righteouſnes may be brought forth as the light,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.6.</note> and his iudgement as the noone day. Let all in authoritie vnder his Maieſtie in Church and Common-wealth, be compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed about with righteouſneſſe. Let the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates put on righteouſneſſe, as a Robe and a Diademe;<note place="margin">Iob 30.14. Pſal. 132 9.</note> and let thy Prieſts bee cloathed: endue thy Miniſters with righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe; yea let vs pray that euery pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate man may haue on him the breſtplate of righteouſneſſe,<note place="margin">Eph.
6.14.</note> that we may offer daily
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5450:12"/>the ſacrifice of righteouſneſſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.5.</note> putting our truſt in the Lord; Oh Lord leade euery one of vs by thy Spirit in the pathes of righteouſnes, vntil thou commeſt to iudge the world in righteouſneſſe,<note place="margin">Pſal.
9.8. Act. 17.31. 2. Pet. 3.13.</note> making a new heauen, and a new earth, wherein ſhall dwell righteouſneſſe. Amen and Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> Secondly, vpon our ſurvay wee exclude from all comfort of this doctrine, the greateſt part of the world which are open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prophane and groſſely wicked, That <hi>hold the truth in vnrighteouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.18.</note> whoſe luſt is there law, who haue no feare of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eyes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 36.1.</note> &amp;c. as yee may reade eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where in the booke of God. Againſt ſuch the wrath of God is reuealed from heauen;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.9. Verſe 10.</note> 
               <hi>Know yee not that the vnrighteous ſhall not inherite the Kingdome of God?</hi> Be not deceiued, neither fornicators, nor ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, nor adulterers, nor effeminate, nor abuſers of themſelues with mankinde, nor theeues, nor couetous, nor drunkards, nor reuilers, nor extortioners, ſhall inherite the Kingdome of God; And is this all their puniſhment? this is puniſhment enough, It is a hell to be out of heauen; yet it were happie for them if they might eſcape with the depriuation of heauen, but they ſhall be turned into hell,<note place="margin">Pſal. 9.17.</note> the place prepared of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5450:13"/>old for the diuell and his angels:<note place="margin">Mat. 25.41.</note> It was principally ordained for the diuell and his angels, but wicked men ſinning doe as it were encroach vpon the diuels right; It is iuſt with God ſince wicked men will ſinne like the diuell, that they be puniſhed with the diuell; But oh thou liuing man! while their is life in thy bodie, there is hope of thy ſoule, if thou wilt turne vnto the Lord he will receiue thee into fauour; as I liue ſaith the Lord, <hi>I haue no pleaſure in the death of the wicked,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech.
33.11.</note> but that hee ſhould turne from his way and liue; Turne yee, turne ye from your euill waies, for why will ye die, ye houſe of Iſrael?
<hi>Diſcite iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiam moniti, &amp; non temnere diuos.</hi> Learne in time before the gate of Gods mercy be ſhut, to <hi>breake off thy ſinnes by righteouſneſſe,</hi> and thine iniquities by ſhewing mercie to the poore,<note place="margin">Dan. 4.27.</note> by a holy reſtitution of wrongs, by the daily practiſe of repentance, if it may be a lengthening of thy tranquilitie, both in this life, and in the life to come, Let my counſell bee acceptable vnto thee, doe not <hi>ſell thy ſelfe to worke wickednes,</hi> and gaine nothing but a roome in hell,<note place="margin">1. King. 21.25.</note> in To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ordained of old; Yea for the King it is prepared (ſaith the Prophet) he hath made it deepe and large,<note place="margin">Eſay,
30.33</note> the pile thereof is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5450:13"/>fire and much wood, the breath of the Lord like a ſtreame of brimſtone doth kindle it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, by this deſcription we alſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe the hypocrite, and ciuill man,<note place="margin"> Luk. 18.9. Prou. 30.12.</note> who haue onely the outward ſhew and conceit of righteouſneſſe, without the inward, ſound, ſolide, and ſubſtantiall change in heart and life.<note place="margin">Math. 23.27,
28.</note> Woe vnto you Scribes and Phariſes, Hypocrites, for you are like vnto painted Sepulchres, which indeed ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare beautifull outward, but are within full of dead mens bones and of all vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; <hi>euen ſo ye alſo appeare righteous vnto men, but within are full of hypocriſie and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie.</hi> Therefore let me ſay vnto you, as our Sauiour ſaid vnto his hearers, <hi>Except your righteouſneſſe exceede the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 5.20</note> 
               <hi>ye cannot enter into the kingdome of heauen.</hi> Ye ſee in what damnable eſtate you are in; ye are in no better caſe then notorious ſinners, nay I feare in worſe; There are moſt woes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt ſuch;<note place="margin">Math. 23.</note> The hypocrite is hatefull to God and man; Fained ſanctity, is accounted double iniquitie, and when God threatneth to puniſh extreamely, hee will giue them their portion with hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites.<note place="margin">Mat. 24.51.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:5450:14"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, wee hence enforce a double exhortation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That euery one of vs would goe out of our ſelues,<note place="margin">Firſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation. Rom. 13.14. Matth. 22.11.</note> and get into the true foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of righteouſneſſe; <hi>Put on the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ;</hi> Put him on as a rich robe of righteouſneſſe, the onely
<hi>wedding garment</hi> of our ſoule; Let vs not content our ſelues with a dreame, figment, and vaine ſhadow of righteouſneſſe, but labour with S. Paul <hi>to be found in him, not hauing our owne righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe which is of the Law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>the righteouſnes which is of God by faith;</hi> If we be not found in him, cloathed with his righteouſneſſe, we ſhal be cloathed with perpetuall ſhame. Let not the enemies of Gods grace, the Papiſts perſwade vs to weaue the ſpiders webbe of our owne workes;<note place="margin">Act. 13.10. Eſay. 39.5.</note> They ſhall not become garments, neither ſhall they couer themſelues with their workes, ſaith the Prophet. Indeede if we preſume to bring before God our workes, they will bee in his ſight but workes of iniquitie,<note place="margin">Verſe
6.</note> as in the ſame place. Yea, Beloued in the Lord, Knowing that a man is not iuſtified by the workes of the Lawe,<note place="margin">Gal.
2.16.</note> but by the faith of Ieſus Chriſt, let vs freely confeſſe,
<hi>In the Lord we haue our righteouſnes and ſtrength;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 45.24.</note>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:5450:14"/>If God ſhould enter into iudgement with vs, no man liuing could be iuſtified.<note place="margin">Pſal. 143.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Doth not Saint <hi>Iames</hi> labour to make men ſee,<note place="margin">1.
<hi>Obiect.</hi> Iam. 2.24.</note> that by workes a man is iuſtified and not by faith onely? And yet S. <hi>Paul</hi> from good premiſes concludes, That a man is iuſtified by faith without the deeds of the Law;<note place="margin">Rom. 3.28.</note> Doe theſe Maſter builders and maine pillars of the Church differ and diſagree, in this fundamentall point of our ſaluation?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> The ſeeming iarres and oppoſitions found in Scripture may be eaſily reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, if we plow with Gods Heifer; S.
<hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh of iuſtification before men, and ſo he maketh workes to iuſtifie, <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuè,</hi> declaring who are to be accounted righteous, in the Court of Sanctification, and by this meanes, the Apoſtle layeth the idle, emptie, verball profeſſour vpon his backe, who onely braggeth of faith, not hauing the fruits thereof, but remaine a dead and fruitleſſe tree, ready to bee cut downe and caſt into the fire. But Saint
<hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of iuſtifying before God, and ſo he maketh the poore hand of faith to iuſtifie <hi>Apprehenſiuè,</hi> apprehending,<note place="margin">Math. 3.10</note> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying, and appropriating the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt vnto the ſinner,<note place="margin">Rom.
4.5:</note> by which
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5450:15"/>the ſinner may with boldnes appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Gods tribunall, in the Court of iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; and by this meanes the Apoſtle beateth downe the proud, conceited, Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaicall Iuſticiary, that dares obtrude and thruſt vpon God his owne good workes, good intents, and good meanings. Yea this ſhall bee found an infallible truth, that Chriſt <hi>came not to call</hi> ſuch <hi>righteous,</hi> but ſinners to repentance.<note place="margin">Math. 9.13</note> The poore Publican that humbly confeſſeth his ſinnes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth Gods mercy in the merits of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Luk. 18.14</note> is the man that goeth away iuſtified ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the other.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>2</label> Doth not Dauid ſay, <hi>Iudge me oh Lord, according to my righteouſneſſe?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 7.8. <hi>Anſ.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer by diſtinguiſhing of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, there is a double righteouſnes, one of the perſon, another of the cauſe,
<hi>Dauid</hi> there would haue God to iudge him, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the goodneſſe or righteouſnes of his cauſe; therefore if thou lookeſt euer to come to heauen, caſt away thine owne righteouſnes as dung and droſſe; For as the Iſraelites did not poſſeſſe the land of Canaan
<hi>for their righteouſnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 9.4.5, 6. Tit.
3.5.</note> ſo thinke not thou to climbe vp to heauen by thine own workes and merits. Let me deale plainely, bee not ſo ſortiſh to thinke of deſeruing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5450:15"/>at Gods hands by thy workes of legall righteouſnes, conſidering what thou maiſt reade in <hi>Job</hi> againſt this conceit,<note place="margin">Iob 22.3. &amp; 35.7.</note> 
               <hi>Is it any pleaſure to the almighty that thou art righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous? or is it gaine to him that thou makeſt thy wayes perfect? If thou be righteous, what giueſt thou him? or what receiueth hee of thine hand?</hi> When we haue done all things commanded vs of God, let vs ſay in truth, and humility, wee are vnprofitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>3</label> Are not we enemies to good works, by this doctrine? Doe we not hinder well do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? May not men ſay, what vſe haue we of good works, when you ſo ſtrictly preach faith onely?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> No, we call as feruently and frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for good workes, as any Papiſt in the world, and vpon farre better grounds; and will any wiſe man ſay; We are enemies to Noblemen; if wee ſaye, that Noblemen muſt not bee Kings? Is there not other good vſe in the ſtate for Noblemen, though they be not Kings, and ſit vpon the Regall throne? So are there not other good vſes of good workes, though they be not admitted to be
<hi>Cauſae regnandi,</hi> and put in the top of Iuſtification? May they not be <hi>Viae ad Regnum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 2.10.</note> wayes that God haue
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5450:16"/>appointed vs to walke in? Is it nothing that our heauenly Father is glorified by good workes?<note place="margin">Mat. 5.16. Gal. 6.10. 2. Pet. 1.10</note> And that our brethren are many wayes bettered by them, and that wee our ſelues are by the ſame aſſured of our effectuall calling and eternal election? And know further, that wee doe not ſo ſtrictly call for faith onely, but that we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire works,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.18.</note> the fruites of faith, to iuſtifie, and teſtifie the life and truth of the ſame faith,<note place="margin">Gal.
5.6.</note> yea although faith, other graces and workes be together in a Chriſtian, yet they doe not iuſtifie together, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre not in the act of Iuſtification; But as the cares and eyes are together in a man, and the eyes onely ſee, and as light and heate are together in the fire, and the heat onely warmeth; So faith, loue, and workes are in a true Chriſtian, but faith (as it is an inſtrument to lay hold, not as it is a vertue, grace, or worke) onely iuſtifieth. To make an end of this matter, we are vndoubtedly to beleeue, that this doctrine of Gods free iuſtification, doth moſt plainely ariſe from holy Scripture; It doth moſt fully e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh the righteouſneſſe of God;<note place="margin">Rom. 3.21, 22, 23, &amp;c.</note> It doth moſt plentifully demonſtrate the deepe miſerie of man; It affordeth moſt ſtrong conſolation to euery true Chriſtian ſoule;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:5450:16"/>for then may Gods Childe ſay with cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and boldneſſe; <hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods elect?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.33.</note> when hee is throughly perſwaded, that <hi>It is God that iuſtifieth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That euery one of vs would <hi>follow after righteouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Second ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation. 1. Tim. 2.22. Pron. 2.20: Luk. 1.6.</note> and daily <hi>walke in the way of good men, and keepe the pathes of the righteous;</hi> that it may be ſaid of vs, as of
<hi>Zacharie</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> they were both righteous before God, walking in all the commaundements and ordinances of the Lord, blameleſſe; though not without all ſinne, yet without open reproofe or blame: So let vs endeauour to be blameleſſe and harmeleſſe, the ſonnes of God,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.15</note> without rebuke, in the midſt of a crooked and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe nation; amongſt whom let vs ſhine as lights in the world.</p>
            <p>To preſſe this point yet further. Let vs but ſeriouſly conſider why God did elect vs; but <hi>to be like to the image of his Sonne?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.29.</note> Why did he create vs, I pray, but that wee ſhould beare and ſhew forth ſome reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of himſelfe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 145.17.</note> 
               <hi>who is righteous in all his waies?</hi> Did hee redeeme vs for any other purpoſe, then to
<hi>ſerue him in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe</hi> all the daies of our life?<note place="margin">Luk. 1.75.</note> were we not made free from ſinne for that very cauſe, that wee might become <hi>the ſeruants
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5450:17"/>of righteouſneſſe?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.18.</note> And wherefore did God reueale his Goſpel of grace (called <hi>the word of righteouſneſſe</hi>) but to teach vs to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vngodlineſſe and worldly luſts,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.11, 12. Heb. 5.13.</note> and <hi>to liue righteouſly?</hi> To what other end ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth Gods ordinance of preaching but to <hi>turne men vnto righteouſneſſe?</hi> Doth not the Apoſtle call true Preachers <hi>the Miniſters of righteouſneſſe?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 12.3.</note> Are not the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which wee receiue <hi>ſeales of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.15. Rom. 4.11. 2. Pet.
2.21</note> I thinke true Religion is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but <hi>the way of righteouſneſſe;</hi> and can we pleaſe God better then by this? or bee any way better aſſured of his loue and acceptation?<note place="margin">Prou.
15.9. Pſal. 11.7. &amp; 45.7. and 146.8. Math 21.32.</note> 
               <hi>Hee loueth him that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth after righteouſneſſe.</hi> And againe, <hi>the righteous Lord loueth righteouſneſſe?</hi> Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how can we thinke to eſcape death and attaine to life, vnleſſe we walke in the way of righteouſneſſe?<note place="margin">Prou. 12.28</note> 
               <hi>Jn the way of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is life, and in the path-way thereof there is no death;</hi> Wee muſt reſolue to finiſh our courſe of well-doing if wee looke for <hi>the crowne of righteouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.8</note> 
               <hi>which God the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous iudge will giue vnto vs:</hi> We muſt not fooliſhly thinke to <hi>dye the death of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 23.10. Pſal. 15.2. Gal. 6.7. Prou. 11.18 Hoſ.
10.12.</note> except we liue the life of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. O vaine world, be not deceiued, as a man ſowe ſo he ſhall reape: <hi>To him</hi> onely <hi>that ſoweth righteouſneſſe ſhall bee a ſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:5450:17"/>God rendreth to euery man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his worke.<note place="margin">Eſa. 32.17.</note> It is <hi>the worke of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that ſhall be peace, and the effect of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, quietneſſe and aſſurance for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Part. </seg>2</label> The ſecond thing which I propounded obſerueable, is, That for the moſt part the <hi>righteous haue</hi> but a poore pittance, <hi>a</hi> very <hi>little</hi> of theſe outward things; when on the other ſide, <hi>many wicked</hi> are full-handed, build there neſts on high, haue <hi>riches,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hab.
2.9.</note> as it is in the text. If we expoſtulate the cauſe with
<hi>Ieremie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 12.1.</note> we muſt acknowledge the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God as he did, and that for good reaſons, hee thus vnequally diſpoſeth and diſpenſeth theſe common things to the wicked and to the righteous.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he dealeth thus bountifully with the wicked for theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To ſhew his abſolute power and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite goodneſſe. <hi>The Lord is good vnto all, his mercy is ouer all his workes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 145 9.</note> He ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth and printeth ſome of his communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble goodneſſe vpon the vileſt of his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and who may controule him, <hi>doing what he will with his owne?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 20 15. Pſal. 17.14.</note> Therefore hee giueth the wicked <hi>their portion in this life,</hi> and they may looke for no more, for euen as <hi>Abraham</hi> gaue all he had to <hi>Iſaac,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 25.5.6</note> and ſent away the ſonnes of his concubines with
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:5450:18"/>gifts, ſo God giueth the wicked outward gifts,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.28</note> reſeruing the eternall inheritance to the children of promiſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To leaue them without excuſe,<note place="margin">Act.
14.17.</note> and himſelfe not without witneſſe, in doing them good, in giuing them raine from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and fruitfull ſeaſons, and in filling their hearts with foode and gladneſſe; Hee can ſay to them as he ſaid to wicked <hi>Saul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.17.</note> 
               <hi>When thou waſt little in thine owne ſight,</hi> I aduanced thee, &amp;c. and they ſhall not be able to ſay vnto him,<note place="margin">Math. 25.24.</note>
               <hi>Wee knew that thou art an hard man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That he might giue vs an example of doing good againſt euill,<note place="margin">Matth. 5.44 45. Rom. 12.20.21. 1. Sam. 24.17.</note> as we may reade in the Goſpel. A dutie too much neglected, yet further commanded by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and practiſed by <hi>Dauid</hi> and many other of the Saints of God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In iudgement many times for their hurt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ. 5.13 1. Tim. 6.9.</hi> Opes irrita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mensa malo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Horat. — Horum ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ego opta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim pauper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimus eſſe bonorum.
<hi>Pſal. 39.6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>J haue ſeene</hi> (ſaith the preacher)
<hi>riches, kept for the owners thereof to their hurt.</hi> So they prooue as a knife in the hand of a childe, or as a ſword in a madde mans hand, dangerous and deadly. Surely many men had neuer beene ſo deepe in ſinne and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie, if they had not beene ſo rich; Euen their wealth through Gods iudgement is a <hi>ſnare</hi> and a <hi>trappe</hi> vnto them.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:5450:18"/>
            <p>To ſay nothing of the care, feare and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row that accompanie the ſame, in getting, keeping and looſing of them; to conclude; As God gaue the children of Iſrael quailes daintie meate, but a plague with it;<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.15.</note> he gaue them their requeſt, but ſent leanneſſe into their ſoule; they had better haue beene without it; So God giueth the wicked the wealth of the world in ſeuere iudgement, as I might enlarge in many particulars. Hence a Reuerend Doctor of your owne was wont to pray,<note place="margin">Doctor Bound.</note> 
               <hi>Giue vs nothing Oh Lord in thine anger, though we ſhould aske it of thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, he dealeth thus ſparingly with the righteous, for theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That hee may bring them to ſome conformitie and correſpondencie, with his Sonne Chriſt there head and elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<hi>who though he was rich,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>yet for our ſakes became poore;</hi> Hee was poore in his birth, life and death.<note place="margin">Luk. 2.7.</note> His birth was not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed a fit roome in a common Inne. In his life, the foxes and foules,<note place="margin">Luk. 9.58.</note> had a more certaine dwelling. At his death he had not a graue of his owne to be buried in;<note place="margin">Ioh.
29.42.</note> 
               <hi>Ergo</hi> they muſt in ſome proportion drinke of Chriſts cup of pouertie; <hi>The Diſciple is not aboue his Maſter.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 6.40.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That he may put a difference, between
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:5450:19"/>the time of our nonage, and the time of poſſeſsing our inheritance;<note place="margin">Gal. 4.1.</note> that wee may ſenſibly diſcerne the time of our ſoiour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning here,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.17. Act. 3.21.</note> from the times of the reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all things; God will not let vs finde a heauen vpon earth,<note place="margin">Math. 17.4.</note> and ſo dreame; <hi>It is good for vs to be here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Being Pilgrimes and Trauellers in their preſent condition,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.13</note> it is not meete they ſhould bee cumbred and loden with too much thicke clay; God will allow vs a light ſtaffe to eaſe vs in our way; but not a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie burden to hinder our progreſſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the wicked may haue occaſion to doe good; that their mouthes may be ſtopped, and they not able to ſay, but that there was ſome <hi>little ones</hi> in eſtate to doe good vnto;<note place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.45. Mark. 14.7. Deu. 15.11</note> according to that;
<hi>Ye haue the poore with you alwaies, and whenſoeuer ye will ye may doe them good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. That he may exerciſe his ſpeciall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in their hearts,<note place="margin">In infortu. nus vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>cet.</note> as Faith, Patience, Hope, Humilitie, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Faith, for if they ſhould haue riches, in abundance, they would goe neere <hi>to truſt in</hi> them;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <hi>in</hi> dead <hi>vncertaine riches,</hi> and not <hi>in the liuing God;</hi> and therefore God often keepeth backe greatneſſe, that himſelfe might be our chiefeſt truſt and ſtay. Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:5450:19"/>God brought <hi>Iob</hi> to a little,<note place="margin">Iob 1.</note> that hee might inure his patience, &amp; in very truth, God by this dealing will trie how willingly we ſubmit, and ſubſcribe to his prouident allowance.</p>
            <p>Hope, He will haue vs hope for a plenty elſe-where;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.19</note> 
               <hi>If in this life onely we haue hope, we are of all men moſt miſerable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Humilitie, becauſe riches doe eleuate and lift vp the heart: God by the Prophet telleth the Prince of Tyrus, <hi>Thou haſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed thy riches</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 28.5.</note> 
               <hi>and thy heart is lifted vp becauſe of thy riches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> He was a heathen and a wicked man, but Gods children are of a better mould, frame and diſpoſition.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Nay, in this point God is iealous of his owne people, that are in ſpeciall couenant with him; He bids them, Take heede that when they haue eaten and are ful, and haue built goodly houſes, &amp;c.<note place="margin">Deut. 8.14.</note> 
               <hi>that their heart be not lifted vp,</hi> and they forget God which brought them forth of the land of Egypt, from the houſe of bondage.<note place="margin">Omnibus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis vt res dant ſeſe, ita humiles aut elati ſumus. Terent. in Hecyra.</note> For the moſt part, as the purſe filleth, the heart ſwelleth; The heathen Poet could ſay as much; <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our outward eſtate, wee are either proud or humble.</hi> It is pitie faire weather ſhould doe hurt; but it commeth often to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5450:20"/>paſſe that in abundance Gods children are ſubiect to ſurfeit; when penury, want, and their competent little keepeth them in good temper;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Viuitur ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iguo meli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</hi> — Prou. 30.8, 9.</note> This made <hi>Agur</hi> pray as heartily againſt riches, as againſt pouerty; <hi>Giue me neither pouertie nor riches, leaſt I bee full, and denie thee, and ſay, who is the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, this doth diſprooue that falſe glaſſe and crooked rule,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Vſe.</hi>
               </note> by which many rich men iudge of their ſpirituall eſtate before God; they thinke themſelues highly in Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, becauſe rich;<note place="margin">Ier. 9.23.</note> but let not the rich man glory in his riches. For alas, this is a meere deceit;<note place="margin">Eccl. 9.1.2.</note> Theſe outward things fall out alike vnto all; or commonly Gods chiefe Fauourites haue the leaſt portion; when prophane
<hi>Eſau,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 27.39.</note> whom God hateth, is allowed <hi>the fatneſſe of the earth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou.
3.16.</note> I tell thee riches are but a gift of the left hand, and if any haue the vantage, it is the poore man. Haue ye not read that God is called,
<hi>the God of the poore and needie, the Father of the fatherleſſe?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>paſſim.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Hath not God choſen the poore in this world, rich in faith, and heires of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which he hath promiſed to them that loue him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 2.5. Luk. 7.22.</note> Yea, <hi>to the poore is the Goſpel prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched;</hi> ordinarily the poorer ſort of people, do giue beſt well-come and entertainment to the ſame,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
26</note> when <hi>not many mightie</hi> and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5450:20"/>rich in the world <hi>are</hi> effectually
<hi>called;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 7.48.</note> 
               <hi>Haue any of the rulers beleeued on him? How hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhall they that haue riches enter into the kingdome of God?</hi> ſuch as <hi>truſt in riches,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 10.23, 24.</note> as is there expounded. Therefore I may ſay to rich and poore,<note place="margin">Ioh. 7 24.</note> Iudge not after the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but iudge righteous iudgement, and alwaies remember that in heauen is poore <hi>Lazarus,</hi> aſwell as rich <hi>Abraham;</hi> pouertie,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.</note> ragges, nakedneſſe, cannot ſeparate vs from Gods loue in Chriſt;<note place="margin">Rom. 8.35</note>
               <hi>He that feareth God and worketh righteouſneſſe is accepted of him;</hi> though he be neuer ſo poore,<note place="margin">Act. 10.35</note> this is ancient doctrine, that God accepteth not the perſons of Princes,<note place="margin">Iob 34.19.</note> 
               <hi>nor regardeth the rich more then the poore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> Secondly, this exhorts vs to contentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hauing <hi>Iacobs</hi> requeſt, foode and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Gen.
28.20. 1. Tim. 6.8. Heb. 13.5.</note> things for the preſent, our portion, our lot, our little, let vs therewith be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; let vs learne with the Apoſtle (a deepe point of Chriſtian learning) <hi>I haue learned ſaith he,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4.11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>in whatſoeuer eſtate I am, therewith to be content; I know both how to be abaſed, and I know how to abound euery where and in all things I am inſtructed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Simus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenti iſta mediocri for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuna, &amp;c. modico, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiola. Weſtmer.</note> 
               <hi>both to be full and to be hungry, both to abound and to ſuffer neede.</hi> Learne then, ſince God hath cut thee out but a little, to bee heartily well content,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:5450:21"/>with his good will and pleaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>1</label> But our little may prooue too little, and ſo we periſh in want, begge, ſtarue in the ſtreete, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I will not goe out of this Pſalme for an anſwer,<note place="margin">Verſe 25.</note> Obſerue the Prophets long expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, <hi>I haue beene yong and now am old, yet haue I not ſeene the righteous forſaken, nor his ſeed begging bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>2</label> We daily ſee that which he did not, the righteous ouer-whelmed with pouertie and beggery.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> If we obſerue, who be the common beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in the world, we ſhall finde the to be the vileſt, graceleſſe, and godleſſe perſons of all the earth; There are but a few Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſſes to be found out of heauen; The wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king diſorderly bringeth and keepeth mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes in the baſe eſtate of beggery,<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 3.11.</note> when religion doth ſo ſchoole the righteous, that he worketh in ſome lawfull vocation, and ſo is not vſually brought to ſo great extrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie. <hi>Salomon</hi> in the booke of Prouerbes is very copious and plentifull in this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſhewing that through ſinfull cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, many miſcreants doe come and crouch for a peece of ſiluer, and a morſell of bread. In particular, <hi>By meanes of a whooriſh wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, a man is brought to a peece of bread.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 6.26.</note>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:5450:21"/>Againe, <hi>The drunkard and the glutton ſhall come to pouertie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 23.21</note> 
               <hi>and drowſineſſe ſhall cloath a man with ragges:</hi> Theſe are the fruitfull mothers that bring forth the numberleſſe troupes of our <hi>euill beaſts and ſlow bellies,</hi> I meane thoſe vnprofitable burdens, the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpillars and deuouring droanes of our Common-wealth, <hi>viz.</hi> the wandring ſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and incorrigible rogues; <hi>Hee becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth poore that dealeth with a ſlacke hand,</hi> but on the other ſide,<note place="margin">Prou. 10.4.</note> 
               <hi>the hand of the diligent maketh rich: In all</hi> lawfull and honeſt <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour there is profit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 14.23.</note> 
               <hi>but the talke of the lippes tendeth onely to penury:</hi> Seeſt thou a lazie, ſlothfull, idle wretch with his hand in his boſome, that can talke of worke but doe nothing? there is more hope of the home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt labourer then of him; the poore plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boy, ſhall come to preferment before him, <hi>He that tilleth his land ſhall be ſatisfied with bread,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 12.11.</note> 
               <hi>but hee that followeth vaine perſons is voyde of vnderſtanding,</hi> and ſo in iuſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion ſhall want bread, and begge in the end as a witleſſe and improuident foole.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>3</label> But wee ſee that God plungeth thoſe, which (you would make vs beleeue) are his onely Fauourites, into a deepe pit of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Wee ſee not things as they are; they are
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:5450:22"/>not ſo poore as we take them to be. Reade what the Script.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.10.</note> ſaith: <hi>As poore, yet making many rich; as hauing nothing, yet poſſeſſing all things.</hi> Not ſimply poore, but <hi>quaſi paupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi> as poore. No, no, God will make hard ſhift (that I may ſpeake it with reuerence) before his children ſhall want neceſſaries, the hard flint,<note place="margin">Num. 20.11</note> the rocke of ſtone ſhall guſh out water, and the hungry Rauen ſhall bring them bread and fleſh in the morning,<note place="margin">1. Kin. 17.6</note> and bread and fleſh in the euening, as it did <hi>Eliah.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13.5.</note> We haue Gods promiſe, that <hi>he will neither leaue vs, nor forſake vs;</hi> and theſe reaſons to induce vs to beleeue the ſame.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Becauſe he prouideth for the vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Creatures:<note place="margin">Pſal. 145.15. &amp; 104.21. Mat. 6.26.</note> The Rauens, Lyons, and the reſt, <hi>ſeeke their meat at God,</hi> waite vpon him, and haue it in due ſeaſon: and will he not feed his owne deare children? Shall they want? No, <hi>the Lyons ſhall lacke</hi> firſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.10</note> and <hi>ſuffer hunger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 He is kind euen to the wicked, which are ſtrangers to his Couenant, his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, <hi>ergo,</hi> hee will not faile thoſe of his owne family, that are vnder his owne charge. If <hi>God</hi> be <hi>the Sauiour of all men,</hi> then eſpecially <hi>of thoſe that beleeue.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim 4.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Hee hath ſuſtained vs heretofore, when we were young: Firſt, when we were
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5450:22"/>in the wombe, before we had a mouth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue meate, his gracious hand made ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſſage: for as in the wombe wee are wonderfully made, ſo are wee admirably preſerued and fed. Then out of the womb,<note place="margin">Pſal. 139.14. Mal. 22.9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>when we yet hung vpon our mothers breſts he was our God:</hi> When we had not a tongue to expreſſe want, yet he made vs cry and bend by a naturall inſtinct to the breaſt of our mother, richly filled with fit ſuſtenance for vs: Afterwards he fed vs when we did nothing, and when we did that which was euill, and can hee now faile vs about his owne buſineſſe? No,<note place="margin">Gen. 48.15</note> he feedeth the godly all their life long.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>He hath giuen vs his Sonne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom, 8.32.</note> therefore <hi>he will giue vs with him all things alſo:</hi> And this is a very ſtrong and Apoſtolical argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: we may reaſon thus: If he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs his Sonne, to be meate, drinke, and cloth to our ſoules, hee will not ſtand with vs for ſo ſmall a triflle, as may ſerue our bodies.</p>
            <p n="5">5 He will giue vs a royall inheritance, therefore we ſhould not feare, that he will ſtarue vs before wee come of age, and are capable of it. <hi>Feare not little flocke, it is your Fathers pleaſure to giue you a Kingdome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 12.32.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 And laſtly, if God doe forſake vs,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:5450:23"/>and not ſufficiently prouide for vs, it is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is either vnable or vnwilling: now for his ability, wee beleeue that hee is Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, and ſo rich in grace to all that call vpon him:<note place="margin">Hag. 2.8. Pſal. 50.10 11.</note> 
               <hi>The ſiluer is mine, and the gold is mine, ſaith the Lord of hoſtes. Euery beaſt of the forreſt is mine, and the cattell vpon a thouſand hils: I know the fowles of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, and the wild beaſts of the field are mine.</hi> In a word,<note place="margin">Pſal. 24.1.</note> 
               <hi>The earth is the Lords, and the fulneſſe thereof.</hi> And for his willingneſſe, that is tranſcendent, infinitely exceeding that of naturall parents towards their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: yea, it ſurmounteth and ſurpaſſeth that compaſsion of the moſt indulgent and tender mother.<note place="margin">Eſay 59.15</note>
               <hi>Can a woman forget her ſucking child, that ſhe ſhould not haue compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion on the ſonne of her wombe? Yea, they may forget, yet wil not I forget thee.</hi> So then, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent thy ſelfe with thy little, foraſmuch as thy litle will proue enough.<note place="margin">Exo. 16.18</note> 
               <hi>He that gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a little had no lacke.</hi> If God giue but a little, he can make a little ſerue the turne, and be enough; and then a little is as good as a feaſt. Is thy prouiſion ſmal? thy appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite ſhall be the leſſe. Remember the ſpeech of the woman in the Martyr-booke;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>M.</hi> Foxe. Acts and Mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ments, pag. <hi>1874.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>If you take away my meate, God I truſt will take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way my hunger.</hi> We know, as it is all one
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:5450:23"/>in reſpect of Gods omnipotencie to worke with meanes, or without meanes: and as good <hi>Jonathan</hi> ſayth, <hi>There is no reſtraint to the Lord to ſaue by many or by few:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sa. 14.6.</note> ſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of Gods ordinary bleſsing vpon the righteous, it is all one to preſerue them by dainty delicates, or by courſer commons; by much or by little. And learne this of, our Sauiour Chriſt, That a mans life con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth not <hi>in the aboundance of the things which he poſſeſſeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk, 12.15</note> but in the goodneſſe of God engrauen vpon them, whereby a few dead things are made ſufficiently ſeruice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to preſerue and maintaine his naturall life, as you ſhall heare by and by.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Part. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, it now remaineth, that I ſhould ſhew, that the eſtate of the righteous with his little, is better then the riches of many wicked.</p>
            <p>Briefly then, as I conceiue the matter, in theſe three reſpects:
<list>
                  <item>1 Becauſe he hath right to his litle.</item>
                  <item>2 Becauſe he hath Gods bleſsing with it.</item>
                  <item>3 Becauſe hee hath power to enioy it.</item>
               </list> Firſt, in that he hath right and iuſt title to his little; it is his owne: now a little of ones owne, is better then thouſands with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out due claime and intereſt, according to that true Prouerbe,<note place="margin">Prou.
16.8.</note> 
               <hi>Better is a little
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:5450:24"/>with righteouſnes, then great reuenewes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out right.</hi> Indeede Gods childe is the right and vndoubted heire of the world; God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs richly all things to enioy.<note place="margin">1. Tim.
6.17.</note> The righteous mans tenure is in Chiefe, in Capite, in his head Chriſt Ieſus; <hi>all are yours, and you are Chriſts:</hi> His aſſurance is Gods firme promiſe; <hi>Godlineſſe hath the promiſes of this life,</hi> aſwell <hi>as of that which is to come;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.22 1. Tim. 4.8.</note> He doth enter or take poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of any thing without prayer; <hi>Giue vs this day our daily bread,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 6.11.</note> remembring that <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery creature of God is good, when it is ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the word and prayer;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.5.</note> His homage, ſuite, and ſeruice is the faithfull diſcharge of his calling, both generall and particular: <hi>With quietneſſe he workes and eates his owne bread;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 3.12.</note> When the wicked haue no right at all (in the court of conſcience) to whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he <hi>haueth and holdeth;</hi> though in the courts of men, he hath a ciuill right, as
<hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſaid to <hi>Ananias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 5.4. Gen.
1.28.</note> 
               <hi>Was it not thine owne?</hi> That vndoubted right once granted to the ſonnes of men is forfeited now, and loſt in <hi>Adams</hi> downfall; ſo that a man out of Chriſt is a theefe, a robber and an vſurper of all that he poſſeſſeth, and albeit he will boldly ſay with Nabal,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 25.11.</note> 
               <hi>My bread, and my water, and my fleſh,</hi> yet they are vnto him
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:5450:24"/>but <hi>vnrighteous Mammon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 16.9.</note> It matters not though he come by them, by reaſon of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, gift, or labour, but then eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are they vnrighteous, when they are got by force, fraud, or any vnlawfull meanes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen or ſecret:<note place="margin">Mich. 6.10.</note> Now doe but weigh in an equall ballance, the meane mans modicum, poſſeſt and held by ſo good and warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a right, and the riches of many wicked, purchaſed and procured, <hi>per fas aut nefas,</hi> by hooke or by crooke, by briberie, periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Simonie, vſury, by the lying tongue, the falſe weight, the ſcant meaſure, the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ware, &amp;c. and then tell me whoſe eſtate is beſt? tell me plainly, Are not <hi>the glea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of Ephraim better then the vintage of Abiezer?</hi> Surely, thou wilt ſay of theſe ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſaid of pleaſure;<note place="margin">Colloq. Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptas non eſt voluptas, quae cum mala fama, mala<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuncta eſt. <hi>Prou. 9.17. Iob 20.</hi>
               </note> Riches are not riches (not worthy any account) when they are ioyned with an ill report and a wicked conſcience; for although ſtolne waters be ſweete to the wicked for a time, yet know that there will be bitterneſſe in the latter end; Marke what
<hi>Zophar</hi> ſaith, handling this very argument of the wicked man that
<hi>oppreſſeth and forſaketh the poore, and violently taketh away the houſe that hee builded not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 19. Verſe
12.13.</note> Though wickedneſſe be ſweet in his mouth, though hee hide it vnder his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:5450:25"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> though he ſpare it, and forſake it not, but <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> keepe it ſtill within his mouth, yet his <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> meate in his bowels is turned, it is the gall of Aſpes within him. He hath ſwallowed downe riches and hee ſhall vomit them vp againe; God ſhall caſt them out of his bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: He ſhall ſucke the poyſon of Aſpes, the vipers tongue ſhall ſlay him; Alas, poore ſoules when the account is made vp of all things gotten by iniuſtice and wrong; this is the totall ſumme,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou. 21.6.</hi> Paululum quod insti poſſident eſt ſuauius &amp; fructuoſius quam impio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum magna affluentia, ob arcanam Dei benedictio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem. Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brard. <hi>Pro. 10.22. Pſal.
113.7</hi>
               </note> viz. <hi>Vanitie toſſed to and fro of them that ſeeke death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in that he hath an operatiue or working bleſsing with his little, to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it both in quantitie and qualitie.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in quantitie, which may be proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by teſtimonies, Diuine, Humane, and Diabolicall.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Diuine, <hi>The bleſſing of God maketh rich;</hi> Againe, <hi>He raiſeth vp the poore out of the duſt, and lifteth the needy out of the dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill,</hi> that is, giueth a large encreaſe to ſmall beginnings.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Humane, old father <hi>Iacob</hi> may bee here produced.<note place="margin">Gen. 32.10</note> 
               <hi>With my ſtaffe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I paſſed ouer this Iordan, and now I am become two bands.</hi> This teſtimonie is vpon record; And may not we confirme this, and ſay to Gods glory, with nothing, or with little we
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:5450:25"/>came into theſe gates, but now God hath multiplyed vs exceedingly. The lines are fallen vnto vs in pleaſant places, yea,<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.6.</note> wee haue a goodly heritage.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Diabolicall, The father of lyes, the diuell vttereth this truth; <hi>thou haſt bleſſed the worke of his hands</hi> (ſpeaking of that righteous man <hi>Iob</hi>) <hi>and his ſubſtance is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed in the land:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 1.10.</note> He acknowledgeth the augmentation of the godly mans wealth to be from the bleſsing of God; ſo that as it is ſaid in the motto, <hi>Concordiâ res paruae creſcunt,</hi> ſo we may ſay, By Gods blesſings ſmal things encreaſe, God we ſee can quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>double</hi> the talents of his faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, ſoone encreaſe <hi>the little oyle</hi> in the cruſe;<note place="margin">Math. 25. 1. King. 17.14. 2. King. 4. Ioh.
6.9.</note> and in the pot of the poore wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, and by his powerfull blesſing, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply the <hi>few loaues</hi> and the <hi>ſmall fiſhes;</hi> When on the other ſide, either the ſecret and hidden curſe of God like a canker, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, waſteth, and vtterly conſumeth the faire eſtates of many wicked, <hi>God bloweth vpon that they</hi> haue, with ſuch a blaſt, as <hi>they ſowe much, and bring in little,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hag. 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>earne wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and put it into a bagge with holes,</hi> as the Scripture ſpeaketh; or elſe ſome open and manifeſt iudgement doe bring them downe from brauery to beggery, from the ruffe to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:5450:26"/>the ragge, from a girdle to a rent as the Prophet threatneth, In ſhort, God ſeemeth to ſay to many wicked men,
<hi>Becauſe you ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not the Lord your God with ioyfulnes and gladneſſe of heart for the abundance of all things;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 3.24.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore you ſhall ſerue your enemies which the Lord ſhall ſend againſt you in hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and in thirſt, in nakedneſſe, and in the want of all things.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 28.47 48. Iob 37.17. <hi>Non horren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da res eſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua et polen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenta. Senec.</hi> 18. <hi>epiſt.</hi> Dan. 1.15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in qualitie, By Gods bleſsing, poore and meane cloathes doe keepe vs warme, and courſe diet, pulſe and pottage doe feed and fat vs. See this in that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent example of <hi>Daniel</hi> and his compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; <hi>Their countenances appeared fairer and fatter infleſh, then all the children which did eate the portion of the Kings meate.</hi> It is not the greatneſſe and daintineſſe of fare, but Gods good bleſsing that doe nouriſh and ſtrengthen the body of man,<note place="margin">Leu. 26.26. Iſa. 3.1. Ha 9.1.6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Mic. 6.14. Prod. 13.25 <hi>Pauxillum pium ſatiat-affluentia impium non ſatiat. Scultet.</hi> Dcut. 8.3.</note> God makes bread to be a ſtaffe and ſtay, to ſatiate and ſtrengthen the righteous man, when the wicked haue the ſtaffe of bread broken, and the ſtay taken away; they eate, eate, eate and are not ſatisfied. <hi>The righteous eateth to the ſatisfying of his ſoule, but the belly of the wicked ſhall want;</hi> In a word, man liueth not by bread onely, but by euery word of God: Now one word of God, is a word of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:5450:26"/>which the wicked haue not. So that as
<hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith of the labourers ſleepe. The ſleepe of the labouring man is ſweete,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.12</note> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he eate little or much, ſo may I ſay of the righteous mans meate, it is ſweet whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be little or much; for the bleſsing of God doth ſo ſweeten and ſeaſon it; that his very appetite and hunger is a ſauourie ſauce vnto it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in that he hath an heart com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably to enioy his little.<note place="margin">Eſay. 3.10.</note> Say ye to the righteous, it ſhall be well with him; for they ſhall eate the fruite of their doing; As it is Gods mercy to reward the righteous for well-doing, ſo it is Gods gracious blesſing, that they taſte, eate and enioy, euen in this life, a part of their reward; That men may ſay.<note place="margin">Pſal.
58.11.</note> 
               <hi>Verily there is a reward for the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, verily there is a God that iudgeth in the earth;</hi> And that this is a ſpeciall fauour, hearken what <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, Behold that which I haue ſeene, <hi>to eate and to drinke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.18 19.</note> it is good and comely for one,<note place="margin">Iuſtus dirigi tur a deo vt ſciat vti di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitijs non eſt avarus non eſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digus, &amp;c. Bellarm.</note> 
               <hi>and to enioy the good of all his labours,</hi> that he taketh vnder the Sunne all the daies of his life, which God giueth him, for it is his portion; Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man alſo to whom God hath giuen ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and wealth, and hath giuen him pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to eate thereof, and to take his portion,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:5450:27"/>and to reioyce in his labour, <hi>This is the gift of God.</hi> When, on the other ſide, there is an euill ſeene of him vnder the Sunne, and it is common amongſt men;<note place="margin">Eccle.
6.1.2</note> 
               <hi>A man to whom God hath giuen riches, wealth, and honour, ſo that he wanteth nothing for his ſoule, of all that he deſireth; yet God giueth him not power to eate thereof, but a ſtranger eateth it,</hi> This is a vanitie and an euill diſeaſe;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Horat. Quo mihi fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas ſi non conceditur vti?</hi> Prou. 15.16, 17. &amp; 17.1. Eccleſ.
4.6.</note> Is not then a little eaten and enioyed, better then abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance laide vp and lookt on? I thinke I cannot conclude better then with that of Salomon, <hi>Better is a little with the feare of of the Lord; Better is a dinner of hearbes; Better is a drie morſell, Better is a handfull with quietnes, &amp;c.</hi> then the abundant ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluitie of many wicked.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> Firſt, hence floweth comfort and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, to all them that haue traced in the way of righteouſnes. Let not the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man forſake his righteouſneſſe,<note place="margin">Ezek. 18.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note> or ſlacke his pace, but rather goe on, ſince the righteous mans eſtate is ſo good, He may ſay as <hi>Iob</hi> in another ſenſe;<note place="margin">Iob 27.6.</note> 
               <hi>My righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe I hold faſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 22.11.</note>
               <hi>and I will not let it goe.</hi> If God be ſo good to the righteous,
<hi>Let him that is righteous be righteous ſtill:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 6.4.</note> Let not thy goodneſſe (O Chriſtian profeſſour) be as the morning cloud, or the earely dewe,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:5450:27"/>ſoone dryed vp and gone away; but as I would haue the ſowe the ſeede of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe in the morning of thy age,<note place="margin">Eccle. 11.6.</note> begin betimes; ſo I would not haue thee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thy hand in the euening, giue in in thy old age; but be faithfull vnto the death;<note place="margin">Reu. 2.10.</note> Yea, ſince God dorh not (in his mercies, graces and bleſsings) forſake vs when wee are old and gray-headed;<note place="margin">Pſal. 71.18.</note> let vs not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake him in our old age, but let <hi>our gray-head be a crowne of glory vnto vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 16.31.</note> 
               <hi>being found in the way ef righteouſneſſe.</hi> Let vs encreaſe in all well-doing,<note place="margin">Prou. 4.18.</note> that our pathes as the ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning light, may ſhine more and more vnto the perfect day.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this may moue all men to bee much affected, yea,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Vſe.</hi>
               </note> euen rauiſhed with this eſtate and happy condition, and to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced with all ſpeed to ſeeke the Kingdom of God, <hi>and his righteouſnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 6.33.</note> ſince all things ſhall be ſo comfortably added vnto them: Let vs labour to be partakers of that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <hi>which conſiſt not in meat and drinke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14.17</note> 
               <hi>but in righteouſneſse:</hi> Let this be firſt ſought after of vs, and it will bee the moſt readie way to thriue in the world: for all things ſhall be ſo added, bleſſed and bettered, as nothing needfull ſhall be wanting to vs.<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.6.</note> It is the onely queſtion in the world, Who
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:5450:28"/>will ſhew vs any good? We that are prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, do ſhew thee,<note place="margin">Mic. 6.8.</note> O man, what is good, and what the Lord requireth of thee: nay, we ſhew thee the good and right way, to encreaſe and <hi>better</hi> thy outward eſtate: It is the Diuels Prouerbe, <hi>He that vſeth plaine dealing ſhall die a begger:</hi> The plaine and iuſt way is the ſure, ſafe, and gainfull way: It is a ſlander to ſay, It is vaine to ſerue God, and what profit is it that wee keepe his ordinances? &amp;c. <hi>Dauid</hi> hath long ſince confuted that ſaying,<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. 3.14. Iob 21.15. Pſal. 19.11.</note> 
               <hi>In keeping Gods righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous iudgements there is great reward.</hi> If we would trie God in the practice of his will, ſee if God would not open the windowes of heauen,<note place="margin">Mal 3.10.</note> and poure vs out a bleſsing, that there ſhall not be roume enough to receiue it:<note place="margin">Hoſ.
2.22.</note> yea, when God hath <hi>betrothed vs vnto himſelfe in righteouſneſſe,</hi> then he will heare the heauens, and the heauens ſhall heare the earth; and the earth ſhall heare the corne, and the wine, and the oyle, and they all ſhall heare vs.</p>
            <p>So long as thou goeſt on (O vaine man) in the way of wickedneſſe, thou art an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>law, out of Gods protection; God neede take no care of thee: But when thou tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt thy feet to Gods commandements, thou mayſt claime the priuiledge of a good
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:5450:28"/>ſubiect, take the benefite of Gods Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and promiſe, wherein God is tyed in little or much, to beſtow vpon thee a great bleſsing: I thinke we may ſay as <hi>Bildad</hi> to <hi>Iob, If thou beeſt pure and vpright,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 8.6.7.</note> 
               <hi>ſurely now he will awake for thee, and make the habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy righteouſneſſe proſperous, though thy beginning was ſmall, yet thy latter end ſhal greatly encreaſe:</hi> ſo it came to paſſe with him; the Text is euident for it,<note place="margin">Iob. 42.12.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord bleſſed the latter end of</hi> Iob <hi>more then his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning:</hi> yea,<note place="margin">Verſe 10. Deut. 28.1.</note> 
               <hi>God gaue him twiſe as much as he had before:</hi> And ſo it will be with thee, if thou ſhalt harken diligently vnto the voice of thy God, to obſerue and to doe all his Commandements, with ſinceritie and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe of heart:<note place="margin">Verſ. 3, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed ſhalt thou be in the Citie, and bleſſed ſhalt thou be in the field: Bleſſed ſhall be the fruite of thy body, and the fruit of thy ground, and the fruit of thy cattell, the increaſe of thy Kine, the flockes of thy ſheepe. Bleſſed ſhall be thy basket and thy ſtore.</hi> And a little after, <hi>The Lord ſhall command the bleſſing vpon thee in thy ſtore-houſes, and in all that thou ſetteſt thine hand vnto, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> Thirdly,<note place="margin">Iam.
2.6.</note> this ſharpely reprooueth the wealthy-wicked, that vſually
<hi>deſpiſe</hi> and diſdaine <hi>the poore</hi> righteous man, and count him as the dung, and off-ſcouring of the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:5450:29"/>world, let them know, that although hee hath but a little,<note place="margin">Pro. 12.26.</note> yet, <hi>The righteous is more excellent then his neighbour:</hi> and againe, <hi>Better is the pore that walketh in his vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 28.6.</note>
               <hi>then he that is peruerſe in his wayes, though he be rich.</hi> And to ſay truth, the righteous poore man, is better then the wicked rich; inaſmuch as righteouſneſſe is better then riches: Now righteouſneſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels rithes, in many particulars, eſpecially in theſe foure: </p>
            <p>1 Riches cannot ſecute vs from Gods wrath,<note place="margin">Prou. 11.4.</note> but righteouſneſſe can. <hi>Riches auaile not in the day of wrath, but righteouſneſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuereth from death:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>We are not redeemed with corruptible things, as ſiluer and gold:</hi> but learne what this meaneth,<note place="margin">Eſa. 1.27.</note> 
               <hi>Sion ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed with iudgement, and her conuerts with righteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2 Riches adorne but the body, but righteouſneſſe decketh and beautifieth the ſoule.<note place="margin">Luk. 16.19. Act. 12.21. Eſa.
61.10. Ezek. 16.</note> 
               <hi>He hath clothed me with the garments of ſaluation; he hath couered me with the robe of righteouſneſſe, as a bridegroome decketh himſelfe with ornaments, and as a Bride ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth her ſelfe with iewels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. Riches cannot giue content;<note place="margin">Eccl. 4.8. &amp;
5.18.</note> neither the eye, nor the heart can be ſatisfied with ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: mans ſpirit, his immortall ſoule can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:5450:29"/>be filled with theſe terrene and tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie things. Wee reade but of one <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>au</hi> that ſaid, <hi>I haue enough.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 33.9.</note> Theſe trifling toyes cannot ſatisfie the vnſatiable heart of a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man;<note place="margin">Matth. 5.6.</note> but they that <hi>hunger and thirst after</hi> true <hi>righteouſnes, ſhall be ſatisfied:</hi> yea,<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.14.</note> he that drinketh of the water that Chriſt doth giue, ſhall thirſt no more.</p>
            <p>4 Riches continue not, they are not permanent and durable; they make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues wings and are ſoone flowne away;<note place="margin">Prou.
23.5.</note> but <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> is called <hi>euerlaſting</hi> by the Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 9.24. Pſal.
82.3.</note> and wee reade of the man that feareth God; <hi>his righteouſneſſe endureth for euer.</hi> Well then, thou that deſpiſeſt Gods poore, God will contemne thee, and ſet thee at naught, and highly exalt his name and memory.<note place="margin">Verſ. 6.</note>
               <hi>The righteous ſhall bee had in euerlaſting remembrance:</hi> and in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place,<note place="margin">Prou, 10.7.</note> 
               <hi>The memory of the iuſt ſhall be bleſſed, but the name of the wicked ſhall rot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, to ſhut vp all in a word, Let vs not <hi>enuie</hi> the vnhappy flouriſh of <hi>the wicked;</hi> as wee are admoniſhed in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of this Pſalme,<note place="margin">Verſe 1. Prou. 24.1. Pſa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1.16.</note> and by
<hi>Solomon</hi> alſo in his booke of Prouerbes. <hi>Habakuk</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to repine at their proſperous eſtate, ſaying, <hi>Their portion is fat, and their meate plenteous:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 21.7.</note> 
               <hi>Job</hi> calleth their eſtate into que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, when he ſaith, <hi>Wherefore doe the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:5450:30"/>liue, become old, yea, are mighty in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer? &amp;c. Dauid</hi> himſelfe ſtumbled at this rocke of offence;<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.</note> Hee was offended at this through ignorance, vntill he went into the Sanctuary of God, and was well catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed concerning the point. Then he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood their end, and would not change his eſtate with them:<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> For <hi>though they proſper in the world, and increaſe in rickes,</hi> yet hee ſaw that God did <hi>ſet them in ſlippery places, and caſt them downe to deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, doe we ſee them aloft vpon the top of Fortunes wheele?<note place="margin">Claud. — Iamnon ad culmine rerum, iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtos creuiſſe queror tollu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in altum vt lapſu gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiore ruant</note> do they build their neſts in the clouds? ſtay awhile, they will not bee long there; they will come downe as faſt as euer they went vp: So ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Man being in honour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth not, he is like the beaſt that periſh: Be not thou afraid when one is made rich, when the glory of his houſe is encreaſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 49.12. Verſe
16.</note> as in the ſame place, neither ſtand amazed, when <hi>they that worke wickednes are ſet vp,</hi> as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prophet ſpeaketh, becauſe,
<hi>Computatis, Computandis,</hi> that is to ſay, in right recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, thou art aboue tenne thouſand times a better man in thy eſtate;<note place="margin">Mal. 3.15.</note> rather pity ſuch as haue no more profit and gaine by that which they poſſeſſe; <hi>What doth it profit a man to gaine the whole world, and to looſe his
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:5450:30"/>owne ſoule;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat.
16.26.</note> And reioyce in thine owne ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage and profite, in that thou doeſt not labour in vaine: <hi>Light is ſowen for the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and ioy for the vpright in heart:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.58 Pſal. 97.11. Phil. 1.11.</note> reioyce in the Lord, ye righteous, for if thou beeſt filled with <hi>the fruits of righteouſnes,</hi> know aſſuredly that <hi>the fruit</hi> of Righteouſnes ſhall be vnto thee a
<hi>Tree of life.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 12.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:5450:31"/>
            <head>
               <hi>I. S.</hi> to the Reader.</head>
            <lg n="1">
               <l> REader, if gladly thou wouldſt be reſolu'd</l>
               <l>Whom God delights in, ſee thou here involud,</l>
               <l>A plaine deſcription of his Fauourite,</l>
               <l>Not the prophane, ne yet the Hypocrite.</l>
               <l>It thwarts the purtnes of the iealous Lord,</l>
               <l>To fauour ſinners, or with them accord,</l>
               <l>But he who out of nature claſpeth ſure,</l>
               <l>By faith vnfeined, on his Sauiour pure,</l>
               <l>Shewes forth his light, abandons wickedneſſe</l>
               <l>And ſerues the Lord in truth, and righteouſneſſe:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <l> NExt, if thou ſeekſt, wherein his fauour ſtands;</l>
               <l>Tis not in worldly wealth, ne goods or lands,</l>
               <l>But in his inward gifts and ſpeciall grace,</l>
               <l>Wrought in the hearts of ſuch as he embrace.</l>
               <l>Let not the rich then in his outward fate,</l>
               <l>Thinke himſelfe happy, and in bleſt eſtate:</l>
               <l>Nor let the poore repine, but reſt content,</l>
               <l>With that ſame little, which the Lord hath ſent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <l> FOr laſtly, here is proou'd how God doth bleſſe</l>
               <l>The little portion that his owne poſſeſſe:</l>
               <l>But cur eth, waſteth, and conſumes the ſtore</l>
               <l>Of rich-vngodly grinders of the poore.</l>
               <l>Let then the righteous man be righteous ſtill,</l>
               <l>And frame his life according to Gods will:</l>
               <l>For though the wicked here exalted be,</l>
               <l>The righteous man is better farre then he.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:5450:31"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
